Hampton L. Carson Papers 1921-1993 Mss.Ms.Coll.83
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Correspondence, 1944-1993; 3.75 lin. feet
  - The MacMillan Company, 1965-1966
    -See also Ser.II, Evolutionary Biology Book Idea
  - Macroevolution Conference, 1980
  - Maddox, Francis, 1959
  - Malcolm, Elizabeth Grace, 1968-1969
  - Manning, Jean, 1977
  - Manning, Raymond B., 1964-1976
  - Mariano, Antonio D. Jr., 1972
  - Martin, Jon, 1981
  - Mathewson, Robert F., 1965-1967
  - Matsunga, Spark M., 1980-1985
  - Matthews, Peter, 1985
  - McDougall, Ian, 1985
  - McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1983
  - Malecha, Spencer, 1970
  - Mayr, Ernst, 1978-1986; 7.0 Item(s)
    -See also Ser.II, Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
    Congratulations, greetings, thanks -- National Academy of Sciences; Drosophila genetics; Publication -- Evolution; Referee's report; Tan, C. C.
  - Merritt, Robert B., 1970
  - Micronesian Mission, 1966
  - Mid-Pacific Marine Laboratory, 1979
  - Miles, Simon, 1979
  - Missouri Botanical Garden, 1975-1976
  - Missouri Conservation Commission, 1944
  - Modes and Mechanisms of Plant Speciation Symposium, 1983-1984
    -See also Ser.III, "Unification of Speciation Theory in Plants and Animals"
  - Monyihan, M., 1960
    Canal Zone Biological Area
  - Moore, John A. and Betty C, 1978
  - Moriwaki, Daigoro, 1971
  - Morton, Newton E., 1972
  - Mosaic, 1984
  - Miura, Robert, 1976
  - Montgomery, S.L., 1976
  - Mull, Mae E., 1980
    United States. Department of Agriculture.
  - Muller, H.J., 1958
  - Nair, Puliyampetta S., 1967-1983
  - Namm, Ted, 1982
  - Narayanan, C.H., 1967-1968
  - National Academy Press, 1980
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1967-1989
  - National Association of Biology Teachers, 1972-1975
  - National Drosophila Species Resource Center, 1982
  - National Drosophila Research Conference, 1982
  - National Institutes of Health Workshop on Population Genetics, 1983
  - National Research Council, 1980
  - National Science Foundation, 1968-1984
    Callahan, James T.
    Scotti, Paul D.
  - Natural History, 1982
  - Natural Resources Defense Council, 1987
  - Nature, 1972-1976
  - The Nature Conservancy of Hawaii, 1989
  - Navarro C., Alfonso, 1965
  - Neel, James V., 1984
  - Nevo, Eviatar, 1972-1983
  - Niederkorn, Jack, n.d.
    -See Ser.I, Heatwole, Harold and Audrey
  - Ohba, S., 1983
  - Ohio State University, 2 folders
    - Bioscience Colloquim, 1984-1985
    - Franz Theodore Stone Laboratory, 1959-1960
  - Ohta, Alan T., 1976-1983
  - Okada, Toyohi, 2 folders
    - Folder #1, 1975-1981
      Gressitt, J. Lindsley
      Entomologia Generalis
    - Folder #2, 1982-1987
      Grimaldi, David A.
  - Oliver, James A., 1964
  - Omenn, Gilbert S., 1978
  - Ordish, R.G., 1967
  - Oster, Irwin I., 1975
    -See also Ser.VI, D. melanogaster--Speciation
  - Owen, Robert P., 1967-1968
  - Pacific Insects, n.d.
    -See Ser.I, International Journal of Entolomology
  - Pacific Science Congress, 1965-1984
    -See also Ser.I, Geo Journal
  - Parker, E. Davis, 1985
  - Parsons, Peter A., 1971-1985
  - Pasadena Foundation for Medical Research, 1962
  - Pastor, Carlos J. Riofrio, 1976-1977
  - Pasteur, Georges, 1986
  - Paterson, Hugh, 1978
    Green, Chris
    Lambert, Dave
  - Patrick, Ruth, 1978
  - Patterson, H.E., 1980
  - Patterson, J.T., 1952
  - Pavan, C., 1976
  - Perkins, David D., 1978
    International Congress of Genetics
  - Phaff, Herman J., 1955
    Dobzhansky, Theodosius
  - Phelps, Julie, 1971
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1962
  - Phillips, John C., 1964
  - Pipkin, Sarah B., 1960-1970
  - Policansky, David, 1971
  - Poulson, D.F., 1959, 1974
  - Powell, D.A., 1973
  - Powell, Jeffrey R., 1977-1985
    -See also Ser.I, Taylor,
    Charles E.
  - Powers, Dennis A., 1972
    -See also Ser.IV, Powers, Dennis A., "Biochemical Mechanisms of Adaptation to Thermal Stress"
  - Prakash, Satya, 1973-1979
  - Proceedings of the Hawaiian Entomological Society, 1982
  - Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 1973-1986
    Selander, Robert K.
    -See Ser.II, same title
  - Provine, William B., 1983; 2.0 Item(s)
    Darwin, Charles; Evolution; History of biology, especially genetics; Research support; Wright, Sewall
  - Pulianas, Glenn, 1976-1977
  - Putnam, [Frank W.?], 1979
  - Pye, Quentin N., 1977
  - Rabor, Dioscoria, 1968
  - Radio Americas, Inc., 1967
    Wilkinson, Robert
  - Radovsky, Frank J., 1977
    Okada, Toyohi
  - Raikow, Rody, 1970-1973
  - Randolph, 1978
  - Raven, Peter H., 1979-1984
    Putnam, Frank W.
    Systematic Botany
  - Reese, Ernst S., 1979
    The British Broadcasting Corporation.
    The Open University
  - Resch, Kathleen, 1970
  - Research Corporation, 1984
  - Richardson, Richard H., 1978
  - Richmond, Rollin, 1976-1985
  - Rick, Charles M., 1978
  - Rico, Marta, 1977
  - Robb, Mrs. David B. (Sarah), 1985
  - Roberts, Henry B., 1967
  - The Rockefeller Foundation
    -See Ser.I Grant, Ulysses J.
  - Rockwood, Susan, n.d.
    -See Ser.I, Rockwood-Sluss, Susan
  - Rockwood-Sluss, Susan, 1970-1976
  - Rocky Mountain Biological Laboratory, 1959
  - Rodell, Charles, 1971
  - Rodenberg, Sidney D., 1978
  - Roig, Roy, 1959
  - Rosen, Leon, 1978
  - Royal Entomological Society of London, 1978-1979
    -See also Ser.II, Royal Society of London--Symposium on Insect Cytogenetics
  - Rubinfeld, Paul Ira, 1970
  - Seaholm, Glen, 1978
  - Selander, Robert K., 1981-1985
  - Sene, F.M., 1976
  - Sheppard, Phillip M., 1973
  - Shields, William M., 1981
  - Shifrine, Moshe, 1955
  - Sabath, Michael D., 1972
  - Sabrosky, Curtis W., 1972
  - Saint Louis Consumer Federation, 1963
  - Saint Louis University, 1966-1967
  - Samuelson, G.A., 1981
  - Samuelson, Shirley, 1982
  - Scandalios, John G., 1983
  - Scheuer, Paul J., 1978
  - Schonewald-Cox, Christine, 1982-1987
    -See also Ser.I and Ser.II, United States. Department of State. Man and the Biosphere Program.
    -See also Ser.III, "The Genetics of Founder Effect"
  - Science, 1964-1982
  - Science as a Way of Knowing Project, 1985-1986
    -See also Ser.III, "Patterns of Inheritance"
  - Scientists for Orlov and Shchansky, 1978
  - Scossiroli, R.E., 1964
  - Scotti, Paul D., n.d.
  - Sigma Xi, 1975-1980
  - Simon, Christine M., 1979-1984
    Archie, James W.
    Ariyoshi, George
    Templeton, Alan R.
  - Simone, Albert J., 1985
  - Sing, Charles F., 1982
  - Singh, B.N., 1973
  - Singh, Madho, 1978-1984
  - Singh, Rama S., 1981-1988
  - Slatis, Herman M., 1963
  - Snyder, 1978
  - Society for the Study of Evolution, 1946-1978; 2 folders
    Business; Conferences and symposia; Editorial matters -- Evolution; Evolution; Population genetics; Publication; Publication -- Evolution; Society for the Study of Evolution
  - Spassky, Boris, 1959
  - Spiess, Eliot B., 1950-1982
  - Spieth, Herman T., 1955-1963
  - Spencer, 1952
  - Stalker, Harrison Dailey, 1967, 1978; 5.0 Item(s)
    Drosophila genetics; Educational matters; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics; Washington University (Saint Louis, Mo.)
  - Starmer, Thomas, 1979
  - Steiner, William W., 1974-1983
  - Stevenson, Richard, 1955
  - Stone, Wilson S., 1955-1956, 1967
  - Strauss, Lewis H., 1984
    Bernice Pauhi Bishop Museum
  - Strominger, Jack L., 1978
  - Stuart, W. Dorsey, 1981
  - Suarez, Teodoro, n.d.
    -See Ser.I, Charles Darwin Research Station
  - Sunset House, 1967
    Conners, George L.
  - Sung, Kee Chang, 1976
  - Systematic Botany, 1984-1985
  - Takada, Harao, 1966
  - Talbot, James J., 1979
  - Tamada, Kathy S., 1982-1983
  - Tan, Soon Guan, 1975-1976
  - Tang, Irene Wei, 1967-1970
    Stalker, Harrison D.
  - Taylor, Charles E., 1977-1979, n.d.
    Powell, Jeffrey R.
  - Taylor-Campbell, Lois, 1972
  - Templeton, Alan Robert, 1970-1984; 60.0 Item(s)
    Biographical and personal data; Conferences and symposia; Drosophila genetics; Evolution; Graduate study; Population genetics; Publication -- Genetics; Recommendations; Reviews; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics; Teaching; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Teremoto, Linden, 1974-1975
  - Thirtle, Barbara, 1974
  - Thompson, James N., Jr., 1977-1985
  - Thomson, John A., 1973
  - Thornton, I.W.B., 1984
  - Throckmorton, Lyn H., 1973
  - Tjio, J.H., 1970
  - Tobari, Yoshiko N., 1983
  - Toda, Masanori J., 1984
  - Tompkins, Laurie, 1986
  - Towle, Edward L., 1970
  - Trifonov, Edward, 1978
    Perkins, David D.
  - Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands, 1965-1966
  - Tsalickis, Mike, 1960
  - Turner, Bruce, 1983
  - Unidentified, 1945-1989
  - United Fruit Company, 1959
  - United States
    - Department of Agriculture, 2 folders
      - Folder #1, 1974-1985
        Bernice Pauahi Bishop
        Museum
        Inoue, Daniel K.
        United States. House of Representatives. Subcommittee on Agriculture, Rural Development and Related Agencies.
      - Folder #2, 1986-1987
    - Department of the Interior, 1978
    - Department of State. Man and the Biosphere Program, 1981-1982
      -See also Ser.I: Clegg, Michael T.; Powell, Jeffrey R.; Schonewald-Cox, Christine; Selander, Robert K.; Templeton, Alan R.
    - Department of Transportation. Federal Aviation Administration., 1967
      Atkins, Gus
    - Environmental Protection Agency, n.d.
      -See Ser.I, University of Hawaii, folder #4
    - House of Representatives. Subcommittee on Agriculture, Rural Development and Related Agencies
      -See Ser.I, United States.
      Department of Agriculture.
  - United States-Japan Cooperative Science Program, 1978-1979
  - University of Arkansas, 1973-1974
    -See also ser.III, "Evolutionary Biology: Its Value to Society"--Lecture
  - University of California, 1963
  - University of Chicago, 1966
  - University of Michigan, 1980
  - University of Hawaii, 1970-1985; 7 folders
    Biographical and personal data; Business; Committee activities; Conferences and symposia; Drosophila genetics; Educational matters; Evolution; Laboratory techniques, equipment; Lectures, public speaking; Population genetics; Teaching; University of Hawaii
    - Folder #1, 1970-1976
    - Folder #2, 1977-1980
    - Folder #3, 1981-1982
    - Folder #4, 1983-1985
      United States. Environmental Protection Agency.
    - Harold L. Lyon Arboretum., 1970-1971
      -See also Ser.VII, "The Ecology of Drosophila Breeding Sites"
    - Research Advisory Council, 1985
    - Workshop on Population Structure, 1972-1973
  - University of Witwatersrand, Johannesburg, 1984
  - Velasquez, Carmen, 1968
  - Villa, Jaime, 1975-1977
  - Vrba, Elizabeth S., 1980-1983
  - Wagner, Warren L., 1985
  - Wahrman, Jacob, 1978
  - Wallace, Bruce, 1973-1983; 3.0 Item(s)
    American Institute of Biological Sciences; Dobzhansky, Theodosius; Evolution; Society for the Study of Evolution; Teaching
  - Ward's Natural Science Establishment, 1952-1956
  - Washington University, 1942-1966
  - Wasserman, Marvin, 1963-1979
    Thompson, James N., Jr.
  - Watanaka, Takao K., 1970-1971
  - Wau Ecology Institute, 1978
  - Weinrich, D.H., 1944
  - Wei, Irene Yi-Lien, n.d.
    -See Ser.I, Tang, Irene Wei
  - Weld, Lewis H., 1952
    Whiting, P.W.
  - Wheeler, Marshal R., 1952-1992; 2 folders
    Drosophila genetics; Drosophila genetics -- Nomenclature; Drosophila genetics -- Sketches; Population genetics; Publication; Teaching; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; University of Hawaii; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
    - Folder #1, 1952-1973
      Heed, William
    - Folder #2, 1976-1992
  - White, Michael J.D., 1971-1978
  - Whitehall Foundation, 1985
  - Whiting, P.W., 1952
  - Wilkinson, Robert, n.d.
    -See Ser.I, Radio Americas, Inc.
  - Wilson, Alan C., 1984-1985
  - Wilson, Mark, 1978
  - Wirth, Willis W., 1964
  - WNET Educational Broadcasting Corporation, 1973
  - Wodzicki, Kazimierz, 1967
  - Woodruff, David S., 1979-1981
    -See also Ser.I, Atchley, William R.
  - Woodward, Dow O., 1982
  - Wool, David, 1985
  - Yankelvich, Efrem, 1978
  - Yanofsky, Charles, 1982
  - Yoon, Jong Sik, 1972-1980
  - Zouros, Eleutherios, 1978-1981
  - Ziegler, Alan, n.d.
    -See Ser.I, Lamoreux, Charles
- Series II. Subject files, 1946-1989; 1 lin. foot
  Symposium programs, including Carson's handwritten notes on lectures given by participants; clippings, biographical materials; reviews of grants, project proposals, and manuscripts; technical reports; and administrative materials relating to professional organizations or university committees on which Carson served. The bulk of the materials are dated between 1970 and 1989. Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic, and items within the files are arranged chronologically.
  - The Academy of Natural Sciences, 1985
  - Accademia Nazionale Dei Lincei, 1981
    -See also Ser.III, "Speciation as a Major Reorganization of Polygenetic Balances"
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences Conference on the Synthesis in Evolutionary Biology, 1974; 2 folders
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1955-1987
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1983
  - The American Naturalist, 1974-1983
  - American Society of Naturalists, 1971-1978
  - Association of Systematic Collections, 1982
    -See also Ser.III, "Speciation and the Founder Effect on New Oceanic Island"
  - Association for Tropical Biology, 1969
  - Australian-American Educational Foundation, 1981
  - Australian Academy of Science, 1985
  - Australian National University. Research School of Biological Sciences., 1985
  - Australian Research Grants Committee, 1978-1986, n.d.
  - Bernice Pauahi Bishop Museum, 1978
  - Biographical Materials, 1971-1981
  - Brigham Young University, n.d.
  - The British Broadcasting Corporation, 2 folders
    - "The Life Game", 1973
    - The Open University, 1978-1980
  - Charles Darwin Foundation, 1976
  - Clippings, n.d.
  - Colonization, Succession and Stability Symposium, 1985
    -See also Ser.III, "Colonization and Speciation"
  - CRC, 1986
  - European Drosophila Population Biology Group, 1975
  - Evolution, 1986
  - Evolutionary Biology Book Idea, 1966
    -See also Ser.I, The MacMillan Company
  - Evolutionary Processes and Theory -- Workshop, 1985
    -See also Ser.III, "Sexual Selection and Speciation"
    -See also Ser.VII, same title
  - Genetic Microdifferentiation in Human and Other Animal Populations -- International Symposium, 1983
  - The Genetics and Biology of Drosophila, 1978
    -See also Ser.I, Thompson, James N. Jr.
  - Genetics Society of America, 1975-1983
  - Genetique, Selection, Evolution, 1985
  - Greater Saint Louis Citizens' Committee for Nuclear Information, 1958
  - Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1982-1983
  - Hapu'u Harvesting Operations, 1979
  - Hawaiian Drosophila Project, 1980
  - HCBI Small Grants Program, 1989. n.d.
  - Heredity and Human Life, 1963-1965
  - Howard Hughes Medical Institute -- Molecular Biology and Evolutionary Theory Workshop, 1984
  - International Congress of Entomology, 1970-1980
  - International Congress of Genetics, 1973-1983
  - International Congress of Evolutionary Biology, 1980-1985
  - Lerner Marine Laboratory, 1964
  - Macroevolution Conference, 1980
    -See also Ser.III,"Stochastic Escape From Stasis"
    -See also Ser.IV, Rosenweig, Michael L., "Evolutionary Theory is Not Even Wounded"
  - Michigan State University, 1983
  - Missouri Botanical Garden, 1959-1975
  - Modes and Mechanisms of Plant Speciation Symposium, 1983-1984
  - National Drosophila Research Conference, 1978-1984; 2 folders
    -See also Ser.III, "Selection for a Courtship-Related Male Character in Drosophila silverstris
    Conferences and symposia; Drosophila genetics; Lectures, public speaking
  - National Institutes of Health Workshop on Population Genetics, 1983
    -See also Ser.III, "New Research Directions in Population Genetics and Evolution"
    See also Ser.IV, Hartl, D.L., "Population Genetics Assessment"
    -See also Ser. IV, Weir, Bruce, "Topics in Population Genetics: Introduction to the Program"
  - National Science Foundation, 1966-1989
  - The Nature Conservancy of Hawaii, ca. 1980s
  - Ohio State University -- Biosciences Colloquim, 1985
  - Pacific Science Congress, 1966, 1983
    -See also Ser.III, "Genetical Processes of Evolution on High Oceanic Islands"
  - Physiological Zoology, n.d.
  - Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 1986-1988
  - Revista Brasileira de Genetica, 1986-1989
  - Royal Society of London Symposium on Insect Cytogenetics, 1979
  - Science, 1981-1984
  - Science and the Media, 1985
    -See also Ser.IV, Locke, Robert, "Hawaiian Medflies"
    -See also Ser.IV, Moore, Barbara, "Scientific Sources' Perception of
    Network News Accuracy"
  - Science as a Way of Knowing Project, 1985-1986
  - Sigma Xi, 1946-1980
  - The Society for the Study of Evolution, 1975-1977
    -See also Oversize
  - The Society for Pacific Evolutionary Biology, 1981
    -See also Ser.II, University of Hawaii. Hawaii Evolutionary Biology Project.
  - Saint Louis University -- Symposium on Meeting the Population Problem., 1968
    -See also Ser.IV, Dobzhansky, Theodosius. "Contribution of Population Genetics"
  - Tri-Fly Eradication Program, 2 folders
    - Folder #1, 1978-1984
    - Folder #2, 1985
  - United States
    - Department of Agriculture, 1986-1987
    - Department of State. Man and the Biosphere Program, 1982
  - United States-Japan Cooperative Science Program, 1978
  - Universita Di Pavia -- Symposium on Genetics of Population Structure, 1954
  - University of Hawaii, 4 folders
    - University of Hawaii, 1972-1984
    - Hawaii Evolutionary Biology Program, 1981-1983
      2 Folders
    - Research Advisory Council, 1985
    - Workshop on Population Structure, 1972
  - University of Michigan, 1956
- Series III. Works by Carson, 1951-1985; 2.75 lin. feet
  Handwritten and typed notes and drafts of reviews, lectures, articles, and a book. This series is arranged alphabetically by title. For each work, the notes, drafts, and published versions are filed together. Lectures contained here are either single or a short series of talks that Carson gave as guest speaker; lectures used in Carson's courses are in Series VI. Works co-authored by Carson appear in this series.
  The works in this series represent Carson's professional and civic concerns. Topics include his scientific research, effects of radiation fall-out on humans, race and human heredity, the teaching of evolution versus creationism, and the modern synthesis of evolution. Letters to Brazil (1951) is one of the earliest works included in this series. This unpublished book manuscript comprises letters that Carson wrote to his wife during his extensive stay in Brazil. The letters, modeled after a similar work by Dobzhansky (see Ser.I, Glick, Thomas), reveal Carson's first impressions and observations of Brazilian life and culture.
  Not individually listed.
- Series IV. Works by others, 1949-1987; 1 lin. foot
  Notes, articles, and lectures written by Carson's students and professional colleagues. Some of the articles were used by Carson as course materials; others were reviewed by Carson for publication. The author best represented is Alan R. Templeton. This series is arranged alphabetically by author and then by title. Works authored by more than one individual are filed under the surname of the first person listed in the by-line.
  - "Parthenogenesis and Inheritance of Spur in D. mercatorum", [Ambul, L.]
  - "Evolution", 31 August 1959; American Society of Zoologists.
  - [ D. mercatorum Mosaics Notes], 1973; Annest, Joseph Lee
    -See also Ser.VII, D. mercatorum -- Mosaics
  - "Systems of Reproduction. II. The Influence of Linkage and Fitness Upon the Genetic Structure of Automictic Parthenogenetic Populations.", Asher, James H. Jr.
  - "Selection for Sexual Isolation of Parthenogenetic Females of Drosophila mercatorum", 1965; Atkinson, Carolyn
  - "Multiple Host Plant Utilization by Chymomyza Amoena in Mid-Michigan via Interspecies Dependence", 1984; Band, Henrietta T.
  - "'Genetic Revolutions' in Relation to Speciation", 1984; Barton, N.H.
  - [Notes on Tests of 1961 Australian Populations of D. mercatorum], 1963; Beitch, Beverly
  - "Sexual Propensity in Drosophila buzzatti", 1964; Beitch, Beverly
  - "Ancient Origin For Hawaiian Drosophilinae Inferred From Protein Comparisons", 1984-1985; Beverley, Stephen M.
  - "Conservation of Gene Pools", 1981; Bishop, John
  - "A Cytological Study of Linear Populations of Drosophila americana Near Saint Louis, Missouri", 1955; Blight, William C.
  - "Genetics and Medical Ethics", 1980; Carlson, Terry A.
    -See also Ser.VI, Genetics and Human Affairs (Genetics 625)
  - "Linkage Studies for Vermillion, Droopy and Ebony Characters in D. mercatorum", 1969; Clemont, Eileen Frances
  - "A Test of the Attraction of Non-Target Insects to a Poison Fruit Fly Lure Composed of a Mixture of Methyl Eugenol and Malathion", 1978; Conant, Patrick
  - [Egg-Counting Data] -- Notes, 1986; Crews, David and Dacanay, Jann Hisae (Takenaka)
  - "Asymmetrical Sexual Discrimination Amongst Three Allopatric Populations of Drosophila mercatorum", 1984; Dacanay, Jann Hisae (Takenaka)
  - "Sexual Performance in a Bisexual Strain of Drosophila mercatorum and Two Parthenogenetic Strains Derived from It"", 2 Folders, 1985-1987; Dacanay, Jann Hisae (Takenaka)
  - "Contribution of Population Genetics", 1968; Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich, 1900-1975
  - "Ecological Variables Affecting the Dispersal Behavior of Drosophila pseudoobscura and Its Relatives", Dobzhansky, Theodosius and Jeffrey R. Powell, Charles E. Taylor, and Michael Andregg.
  - [Cilia of Drosophila silvestris], 1980; Val, Francisca Carolina do
  - "Reproductive Isolation in a Neotropical Insect: Behavior and Microbiology", 1986; Ehrman, Lee
  - "Diploidization in the Eggs of Parthenogenetic Strains of D. mercatorum", 1973; Freire-Maia, dertia
  - "Some Aspects of Early Development in Drosophila Thelytokytes", Geckeler, Bill
  - "Population Genetics Assessment", 1983; Hartl, D.L.
  - "Sexual Isolation in a Parthenogenetic Strain of Drosophila mercatorum", 1965-1966; Henslee, Earl Dean
  - "Genetic and Environmental Determinants of Food Preference in Drosophila tripunctata", 1984; Jaenike, John
  - "Evolution in Hybrid Dysgenesis Determinants in Drosophila melanogaster", 1982; Kidwell, Margaret G.
  - Oviposition on Yeasts -- Notes, 1956; Kinsley, Richard N. Jr.
  - [Notes on Drosophila Crosses], Lipke, Mary Ann
  - "Hawaiian Medflies", 1985; Locke, Robert
    -See also Ser.II, Science and the Media
  - "The Evolution of Insect Resistance to Malathion", 1981; Lohrman, Donna
  - "Outline Geology of Papau New Guinea", 1976; Manser, W.
  - "How I Became a Darwinian", 1974; Mayr, Ernst, 1904-2005
  - "Some Informal Comments Recorded While Reading White's Modes of Speciation", 1978; Mayr, Ernst, 1904-2005
  - "Scientific Sources' Perception of Network News Accuracy", 1985; Moore, Barbara and Michael Singletary
    -See also Ser.II, Science and the Media"
  - "The Drosophila of Southern California. I. Colonization After a Fire", ca. 1974; Moore, John A., Charles E. Taylor and Betty C. Moore
  - "Mercury Selection of Allozymes in Marine Organisms: Prediction and Verification in Nature", 1983; Nevo, Eviatar, Rachael Ben-Shlomo and Batia Lavie
    -See also Ser.I, Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
  - "Synhospitalic Evolution of Drosophilella Species" -- Lecture, 1980; Okada, Toyohi
    -See also Ser.II, International Congress of Entomology
    -See also Ser.III, "The Ecology and Evolution of Some Flower-Breeding Drosophilidae of New Guinea'' -- Lecture
  - "Biochemical Mechanisms of Adaptation to Thermal Stress", 1972; Powers, Dennis A.
  - "Parthenogenetic Diploidization in Drosophila mercatorum", 1970; Ragan, Joanne
  - "Evolutionary Theory is Not Even Wounded", 1980; Rosenzweig, Michael L.
    -See also Ser.II, Conference on Macroevolution